openpr.com 2019-04-06

# Privacy Policy of the Einbock GmbH

This Privacy Policy clarifies the nature, scope and purpose of the processing of personal data (hereinafter referred to as "Data") within our websiteing and the related websites, features and content, as well as external online presence, e.g. our social media profiles on. (collectively referred to as "website"). With regard to the terminology used, e.g. "Personal data" or their "processing", we refer to the definitions in Article 4 of the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR).

## 1\. Responsible

Responsible for the data processing is:  
Einbock GmbH  
Prinzenstr. 1  
30159 Hanover  
District Court Hannover, HRB 209511  
Managing Director: Lawyer Sebastian Einbock

## 2\. External data protection officer

You can contact our external data protection officer at the following contact details:  
Ferzen Agirman  
c / o Einbock GmbH, Prinzenstr. 1, 30159 Hanover  
E-Mail: [datenschutz@einbock.com](mailto:datenschutz@einbock.com)  
Fax: +49 (0) 511-47397781

## 3\. Types of processed data

3.1 We process data of the following data categories:

  * Inventory data (e.g., names, addresses);
  * contact information (e.g., e-mail, phone numbers);
  * Content data (e.g., text inputs, photographs, videos);
  * contract data (e.g., subject, term, customer category);
  * payment data (e.g., bank details, payment history);
  * usage data (e.g., websites visited, interest in content, access times);
  * Meta / communication data (e.g., device information, IP addresses).

3.2 Processing of special categories of data (Article 9 (1) GDPR) 

In principle, no special categories of data are processed unless they are sent by the users to the processing, e.g. entered in online forms.

3.3. Categories of data subjects

Employed data / customers / prospects / suppliers / employees Data of customers or suppliers, visitors and users of the websites. In the following, we also refer to the persons concerned as "users".

## 4\. Purpose of the processing

Below is a list of the purposes of the processing:

  * Providing the website, its contents and functions;
  * provision of contractual services, service and customer care;
  * answering contact requests and communicating with users;
  * marketing, advertising and market research;
  * Safety measures.

## 5\. Legal basis of the data processing

In accordance with Art. 13 GDPR, we inform you about the legal basis of our data processing. Unless the legal basis in the data protection declaration is mentioned, the following applies: The legal basis for obtaining consent is Article 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. a) and Art. 7 GDPR, the legal basis for the processing for the performance of our services and the performance of contractual measures as well as the response to inquiries is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) GDPR, the legal basis for processing in order to fulfill our legal obligations is Article 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. c) GDPR, and the legal basis for processing in order to safeguard our legitimate interests is Article 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR. In the event that vital interests of the data subject or another natural person require the processing of personal data, Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. d) GDPR as legal basis.

## 6\. Collaboration with processors and third parties

6.1. If, in the context of our processing, we disclose data to other persons and companies (contract processors or third parties), transmit them to them or otherwise grant access to the data, this will only be done on the basis of a legal permission (eg if a transmission of the data to third parties, as to payment service providers, pursuant to Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 (b) GDPR is required to fulfill the contract), you have consented to a legal obligation or on the basis of our legitimate interests (eg the use of agents, web hosts, Etc.).

6.2. If we commission third parties to process data on the basis of a so-called "contract processing contract", this is done on the basis of Art. 28 GDPR.

## 7\. Transfers to third countries

If we process data in a third country (ie outside the European Union (EU) or the European Economic Area (EEA)) or in the context of the use of third party services or disclosure or transmission of data to third parties, this will only be done if it is to fulfill our (pre) contractual obligations, on the basis of your consent, on the basis of a legal obligation or on the basis of our legitimate interests. Subject to legal or contractual permissions, we process or have the data processed in a third country only in the presence of the special conditions of Art. 44 et seq. GDPR. That the processing is e.g. on the basis of specific guarantees, such as the officially recognized level of data protection (eg for the US through the Privacy Shield) or observance of officially recognized special contractual obligations (so-called "standard contractual clauses").

## 8\. Cookies and right to object to direct mail

8.1. Cookies" are small files that are stored on users' computers. Different information can be stored within the cookies. A cookie is primarily used to store the information about a user (or the device on which the cookie is stored) during or after his visit to the website. Temporary cookies, or "session cookies" or "transient cookies", are cookies that are deleted after a user leaves an online service and closes his browser. In such a cookie, e.g. the contents of a shopping cart in an online shop or a login status are saved. The term "permanent" or "persistent" refers to cookies that remain stored even after the browser has been closed. Thus, e.g. the login status will be saved if users visit it after several days. Likewise, in such a cookie the interests of the users can be stored, which are used for range measurement or marketing purposes. A "third-party cookie" refers to cookies that are offered by providers other than the person who manages the website (otherwise, if it is only their cookies, this is called "first-party cookies").

8.2. We can use temporary and permanent cookies and clarify this in the context of our privacy policy.

8.3. If users do not want cookies stored on their computer, they will be asked to disable the option in their browser's system settings. Saved cookies can be deleted in the system settings of the browser. The exclusion of cookies can lead to functional restrictions of our websites.

8.4. A general contradiction to the use of cookies used for online marketing purposes can be found in a variety of services, especially in the case of tracking, via the US website <http://www.aboutads.info/choices/> or the EU site <http://www.youronlinechoices.com/> (under "Preferences"). Furthermore, the storage of cookies can be achieved by switching them off in the settings of the browser. Please note that not all features of our websites may be used.

## 9\. Deletion of data

9.1. The data processed by us are deleted or limited in their processing in accordance with Articles 17 and 18 GDPR. Unless explicitly stated in this privacy policy, the data stored by us are deleted as soon as they are no longer required for their purpose and the deletion does not conflict with any statutory storage requirements. Unless the data is deleted because it is required for other and legitimate purposes, its processing will be restricted. That The data is blocked and not processed for other purposes. This applies, for example for data that must be kept for commercial or tax reasons or for data whose further storage is required for evidence purposes.

9.2. According to legal requirements, the storage takes place in particular for 6 years in accordance with § 257 paragraph 1 HGB (trading books, inventories, opening balance sheets, annual accounts, trade letters, accounting documents, etc.) and for 10 years in accordance with § 147 Abs. 1 AO (books, records, management reports , Accounting documents, commercial and business letters, documents relevant to taxation, etc.).

## 10\. Provision of contractual services (webshops) 

10.1. We process stock data (eg company, title / academic degree, names and addresses as well as contact data of users, e-mail), contract data (eg services used, names of contact persons) and payment data (eg bank details, payment history) for the purpose of fulfilling our contractual obligations (Knowledge of who is the contracting party, justification, content design and execution of the contract, verification of the plausibility of the data) and services (eg contacting the customer service) acc. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) GDPR. The entries marked as obligatory in online forms are required for the conclusion of the contract.

10.2. A transfer of this data to third parties is not, unless it is necessary for the prosecution of our claims (for example, transfer to lawyer for debt collection) or there is a legal obligation in accordance with. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. c) GDPR.

10.3. We may also process the information you provide to inform you of other interesting products from our portfolio or to send you e-mail with technical information.

10.4. The data will be deleted as soon as it is no longer necessary for the purpose of its collection. This is the case for the inventory and contract data if the data for the execution of the contract are no longer required and no claims can be asserted from the contract, because these are barred (statute of limitations: three years). Due to commercial and tax regulations, we are obliged to save your address, payment and order data for a period of ten years. However, at the end of the contract, we will postpone processing after three years. H. Your data will only be used to comply with legal obligations. Information in the user account remains until it is deleted.

## 11\. Use of blog functions / comments

11.1. You can post public comments on our blog, where we post various contributions to topics on our website. Your comment will be posted to the post with your given username. We recommend using a pseudonym instead of your common name. The username and e-mail address are required, all other information is optional.

11.2. When you leave a comment, we will continue to save your IP address, which we delete after 70 days. The storage is necessary for us to defend ourselves in cases of possible publication of illegal content against liability claims. We need your e-mail address to contact you if a third party objected to your comment as unlawful.

11.3. Legal bases are Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) and f) GDPR.

11.4. Comments will not be reviewed prior to publication. We reserve the right to delete comments if they are objected to by third parties as unlawful. A transfer of these data to third parties does not take place, unless it is necessary for the prosecution of our claims or there is a legal obligation in accordance with. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1. lit. c) GDPR. The data will be deleted as soon as they are no longer necessary for the purpose of their collection or the execution of the contract, because the contract has been terminated.

## 12\. Use of our forum

12.1. Our forum can be read without registration. If you would like to actively participate in the forum, you must register by stating your e-mail address, name and your user name. There is no common name compulsion, a pseudonymous use is possible. We use the so-called double-opt-in procedure for registration. H. Your registration is only completed if you have previously confirmed your registration via a confirmation email sent to you for this purpose by clicking on the link contained therein. If your confirmation is not received within 24 hours, your registration will be automatically deleted from our database.

12.2. When you sign up for a forum account, we will store all the information you post in the forum, such as public posts, bulletin board entries, friendships, private messages, and more, until your sign off, to run the forum. We need your e-mail address in order to contact you if a third party objected to your contribution being unlawful. When you post in the forum, we will continue to save your IP address, which we delete after 70 days. The storage is necessary for us from the legitimate interest, in order to defend ourselves in cases of possible publication of illegal content against liability claims.

12.3. The legal basis is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) and f) GDPR.

12.4. If you delete your account, your public statements, in particular contributions to the forum, remain visible to all readers, but your account is no longer available and marked in the forum with "Guest". All other data will be deleted. If you wish your public contributions to be deleted as well, please contact the person responsible under the above contact details.

## 13\. Registration / user account 

13.1. On our website, we offer users the possibility to register themselves (user account) by providing personal data (eg company, title / academic degree, names and addresses as well as contact data of users, e-mail). The data is entered into an input mask and transmitted to us and stored. A transfer of data to third parties does not take place. At the time of registration, the following data is also stored: The IP address of the user, date and time of registration. We use the so-called double-opt-in procedure for registration. H. Your registration is only completed if you have previously confirmed your registration by sending a confirmation e-mail sent to you for this purpose by clicking on the link contained therein or by sending a fax with the confirmation. If your confirmation is not received within 30 days, your registration will be automatically deleted from our database. The specification of the aforementioned data is mandatory, all other information you can volunteer by using our portal.

13.2. A registration of the user is necessary for the fulfillment of a contract with the user (determination of the identity of the contracting party, data for the establishment of contact) or for the implementation of pre-contractual measures. The legal basis for the processing of the data upon registration is to fulfill a contract of which the user is a party or to carry out pre-contractual measures Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) GDPR.

13.3. If necessary, we analyze information from the service provider maxmind inc. 14 Spring Street, 3rd Floor, Waltham, MA 02451, United States (<https://www.maxmind.com/privacy_policy)> Your IP in terms of origin (GeoIP) and whether it is a proxy (proxy score). The circumstance and the result of our inquiry will be added to your user account for the duration of the contractual relationship. The storage is based on our legitimate interests, as well as the user's protection against misuse / fraud and other unauthorized use. The legal basis for this is Article 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR.

13.4. As a user, you always have the option of changing the data stored about you at any time. If the data is required to fulfill a contract or to carry out pre-contractual measures, premature deletion of the data is only possible, unless contractual or legal obligations preclude deletion. In this case, the regulations for the provision of contractual services under Zif. 6 ..

## Online payment provider

14.1. The settlement takes place with payment by "Paypal" over PayPal (Europe) S.à r.l. et Cie, S.C.A., 22-24 Boulevard Royal, L-2449 Luxembourg, Web: paypal.de, <https://www.paypal.com/de/webapps/mpp/ua/privacy-full.> The settlement takes place when paying via "virtual VR-Pay" for credit card payments via Hannoversche Volksbank eG, Kurt-Schumacher Str. 19, 30159 Hannover, Web: vr-pay.de, <https://www.vr-pay.de/> data protection liability / by visa, <https://www.visa.de/datenschutz>, Mastercard, <https://www.mastercard.de/de-de/datenschutz.html> or American Express, [https://www.americanexpress](https://www.americanexpress/). com / de / content / privacy-policy-statement.html.The settlement takes place with payment over "Sofort.com" over Klarna GmbH, Theresienhöhe 12, 80339 Munich, [https://www.klarna.com/sofort/datenschutz/.](https://www.klarna.com/sofort/datenschutz/) Hereinafter called "Online Settlers". The online payers collect, store and process the usage and billing data of the user for the purpose of determining and billing the service used by him. The data entered in the online accounts are only processed and stored by them. If the online payers can not or only partially collect the user fees or the on-line payers fail to do so due to a complaint by the user, the usage data will be passed on by the online payee to the person responsible and the user may be blocked by the responsible person. The same applies if e.g. a credit card company reverses a transaction of the user.

14.2. The legal basis is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. b) GDPR, as processing is required to fulfill a contract by the controller. In addition, external online settlements are calculated on the basis of Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR from legitimate interests of the person responsible in order to be able to offer the user the most secure, simple and varied payment options possible.

14.3. With regard to the storage period, rights of revocation, information and data protection, we refer to the above data protection statements of the online payers.

## 15\. Financial Accounting

15.1. In the context of financial accounting and statutory filing obligations (GoBD), we process the same data that we provide in the context of the provision of our contractual services according to Zif. 6 process. The legal basis is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. c) and f) DSGVG. Affected are customers, prospects and users of our websites. The purpose of the processing is the commercial and tax law obligation for financial accounting and archiving of data. We also have a legitimate interest in maintaining our business and proper office organization. The deletion of contractual and contractual data in accordance with the information given under Zif. 6th.

15.2. These data will be passed on to the following third parties: to the tax office / auditors and tax consultants as well as to other authorities, insofar as there is a legal obligation to do so.

## 16\. Contact via contact form / E-Mail / Fax / Post

16.1. When contacting us via contact form, fax, mail or e-mail, the details of the user are processed for the purpose of processing the contact request. Legal basis for the processing of the data is in the presence of the consent of the user Art. 6 para. 1 p. 1 lit. a) GDPR. The legal basis for the processing of the data transmitted in the course of sending an e-mail, letter or fax is Article 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR. The person in charge has a legitimate interest in the processing and storage of the data in order to be able to answer user inquiries by e-mail, letter or fax, to safeguard evidence for reasons of liability and, if necessary, to fulfill his statutory retention requirements for business letters. If the e-mail / post / fax contact is aimed at the conclusion of a contract, additional legal basis for the processing is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) GDPR. When contacting via a contact form, your declaration of consent pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows:

" **I have read the**[ **privacy policy**](https://www.einbock.com/datenschutz-en) **and agree that my personal data entered in the form will be stored and processed for the purpose of processing my request.** You can revoke your consent at any time."

16.2. User information can be stored in our Customer Relationship Management System ("CRM System") or similar request organization.

16.3. The data will be deleted as soon as it is no longer necessary for the purpose of its collection. For the personal data from the input form of the contact form and those sent by e-mail, this is the case when the respective conversation with the user has ended. The conversation is ended when it can be inferred from the circumstances that the relevant facts have been finally clarified. Inquiries from users who have a user account, we store permanently and refer to the registration details Zif. 9 or provision of contractual services Zif. 6. In the case of legal archiving obligations, the deletion takes place after its expiry (end of commercial law (6 years) and tax law (10 years) retention obligation).

16.4. At any time, you have the option of obtaining consent in accordance with Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a) to revoke the GDPR for the processing of personal data. If you contact us by e-mail, you may object to the storage of your personal data at any time.

## 17\. Contact by phone

17.1. When contacting us by telephone, the telephone number of the user is processed to process the contact request and their processing and temporarily stored or displayed in the RAM / cache of the telephone / display. The storage is made for reasons of liability and security in order to be able to prove the call as well as for economic reasons in order to enable a recall. In the case of unauthorized advertising calls, we block the phone numbers.

17.2. The legal basis for processing the telephone number is Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR. If the contact is aimed at the conclusion of a contract, additional legal basis for the processing is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. b) GDPR.

17.3. The device cache stores the calls for 30 days and overwrites or deletes old data successively; when the device is disposed of, all data is deleted and the memory is destroyed if necessary. Blocked phone numbers are checked annually for the need for blocking.

17.4. You can prevent the phone number from being displayed by calling with the phone number suppressed by default.

## 18\. Advertising mailing by mail (B2B)

18.1. We also use postal advertising for potential customers for direct mail. We process and store the following data: Company, title / academic degree, occupation, title, name, address. The mailings are sent by a lettershop in Germany, with which there is an agreement for order processing according to Art. 28 GDPR. Otherwise the data will not be passed on to third parties.

18.2. The legal basis for this is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR (or before 25.5.2018: § 28 (3) p. 2 BDSG a.F ..)

18.3. The purpose of using mailings is to attract B2B new customers to our company. Our legitimate interest in the processing of personal data pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR. This is based on the following balance of interests:  

  * For consideration, recital (EC) 47 GDPR should be used: "The processing of personal data for the purpose of direct marketing may be considered as processing of legitimate interest." In addition, EC 47 DSG Regulation provides, with regard to balance of interests, "the reasonable expectations of the parties concerned Persons based on their relationship with the person responsible ". For the reasonable expectations of the data subject, especially Articles 13 and 14 GDPR are to be used. In addition, according to EC 47 GDPR, it must be considered whether the data subject is already a customer of the person responsible or uses his services. Finally, the "Principles for processing personal data" under Art. 5 GDPR are to be used.
  * We offer services and products for companies in the field of law, PR / marketing and home / garden. These help customers to advertise new customers or simplify their processes. Therefore, it is generally assumed that the customers will find our offers useful. We have an interest in advertising to new customers who are not existing customers. It is to be expected that new customers will also find the offers useful ("reasonable expectations of the persons concerned").
  * The interest in direct mail is also supported by the focus on B2B customers, where the selection criteria are based on information about the company, e.g. Law firms, and not individuals. No data are collected from the personal environment of the customers or from special categories according to Art. 9 para. 1 GDPR. Likewise, no information from other sources such as social networks are taken into account or so-called advertising scores are created. The missing aggregation of selection criteria means a low intervention intensity.
  * Law firms must also publish their contact details in accordance with § 21 BRAO in the telephone directory in the context of the law firm's duty to register. a special interest in acquiring new clients. You have to make yourself "public" to make contact. This is comparable with other companies, which want to be reachable also for their customers, but also interesting offers. Therefore, our direct advertising measures are mainly used for offers for client / customer acquisition of those affected. Lawyers can count as entrepreneurs on the use of their data for the purpose of marketing due to the professional obligation to publish their contact.
  * Therefore, we also research addresses from publically accessible sources / directories or homepages of companies. There is no storage of further data.
  * On the other hand, there is little interest on the part of the person concerned, not to receive direct mail from us as a company not previously contracting with them. Industry-specific B2B letter advertising has only a minor impact on the business process an interest of the persons concerned suspect. It should also be borne in mind that the persons or companies concerned by the postal advertising can prevent the advertising by attaching a note to the mailbox that they do not wish to receive a sales letter, since the postmen are generally instructed to send the sales letter marked "Dialogpost" not deliverable. As a result, a burden on the office organization by the affected parties can be easily avoided in advance. Due to the obligation to pay, direct mail by mail is also generally smaller in numbers than by electronic means and therefore less burdensome. Finally, there is a right to object at any time under Article 21 (2) of the GDPR, to which the parties concerned must expressly be informed in accordance with Article 21 (4) of the GDPR. According to Art. 21 (3) GDPR, personal data may not be processed and used for advertising purposes if there is an advertising conflict. Therefore, an interest of data subjects or companies in the exclusion of data processing does not prevail due to the previous considerations.

18.4. The data is deleted as soon as it is no longer necessary for the purpose to be achieved or the data subject objects to the processing. The objection may be made by e-mail, fax or post to the above contact details.

## 19\. Contests

19.1. For the purpose of competitions, the e-mail address will be stored to contact you, and in the case of the win, the address data to be able to send the prize. The address data can be passed on to a dispatcher. Any other transfer of the data to third parties will not take place.

19.2. The legal basis is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) GDPR.

19.3. The data will be deleted 2 months after the determination of the profit.

## 20\. Contact mediation to third parties

20.1. When contacting a third party (via contact form or e-mail), the information provided by the user to process the contact request and its processing in accordance with. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a) and b) GDPR processed and forwarded to the desired recipient (third party) by electronic means by fax or e-mail. For this we send faxes with the service simple-Fax.de the company simple Communication GmbH, Salzdahlumer Str. 196, 38126 Braunschweig, with which there is an agreement for order processing according to Art. 28 GDPR. When contacting via the contact placement form, your declaration of consent pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows:

" **Yes, I agree that my personal data entered in the form will be transmitted and stored unencrypted by fax and e-mail to the person to be contacted for the purpose of offering the offer.** This consent, which can be revoked at any time, as well as the processing and data transmission by third parties, are carried out in accordance with Art. our privacy policy. "

20.2. User information can be stored in our Customer Relationship Management System ("CRM System") or similar request organization.

20.3. We delete the requests, if they are no longer required. We check the necessity every two years; Inquiries to users who have a user account, we store permanently and refer to the registration information for deletion.

20.4. At any time, you have the option of obtaining consent in accordance with Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a) to revoke the GDPR for the processing of personal data. If you contact us by e-mail, you may object to the storage of your personal data at any time. 21 reviews 21.1. In the evaluation of users (via online evaluation form), the details of the evaluator to process the evaluation acc. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a) and b) GDPR processed and forwarded to the evaluated user by electronic means by e-mail for information. When assessing the evaluation form, your declaration of consent was in accordance with Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows: "Yes, I agree that my personal data (name, email, IP) entered in the" Assessment "form will be stored and sent to the valuer for the purpose of verifying that a contract has been concluded with the assessed person. My rating will be published anonymously. You can revoke this consent at any time. The evaluation takes place acc. our privacy policy. "

## 21\. reviews

21.1. In the evaluation of users (via online evaluation form), the details of the evaluator to process the evaluation acc. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a) and b) GDPR processed and forwarded to the evaluated user by electronic means by e-mail for information. When assessing the evaluation form, your declaration of consent was in accordance with Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows:

"Yes, I agree that my personal data (name, email, IP) entered in the" Assessment "form will be stored and sent to the valuer for the purpose of verifying that a contract has been concluded with the assessed person. My rating will be published anonymously. You can revoke this consent at any time. The evaluation takes place acc. our privacy policy. "

21.2. All ratings are published anonymously and serve the neutral information transfer. Merely to check if there was a contract between the evaluator and the rated user, you have to state your e-mail as well as the first and last names in the evaluation, which we store and process for the purpose. The user you have reviewed can see this data to uniquely assign the rating and, if necessary, comment on it. We forward your rating to the valued user by e-mail for information.

21.3. We will delete the ratings if they are no longer required if the contractual relationship ends with the rated user. We will delete your personal data 90 days after the evaluation, unless it is their further storage for evidence is required, then these are excluded until the final clarification of the respective incident of the deletion.

## 22\. pattern generator

22.1. You have the option to generate a sample imprint and a privacy statement by providing personal data (company, name, address, telephone, e-mail). The data is entered into an input mask and transmitted to us and stored. A transfer of data to third parties will not take place, unless there is a legal obligation. The specification of the aforementioned data is mandatory, all other information you can voluntarily provide when using the generator. This is for the purpose of ensuring proper use of the generator and the texts as well as documentation for you. The legal basis for processing the data is Article 6 (1) sentence 1 (b) GDPR.

22.2. At the time of use, the following data is also saved: IP address of the user, date and time. Our legitimate interest is as follows: Protection against misuse and the resolution of copyright infringement is only a small interference with your rights. The legal basis for this is Art. 6 para. 1 p. 1 f) GDPR.

22.3. The data will be deleted as soon as they are no longer necessary for the achievement of the purpose of their collection or the execution of the contract, because the contract has been terminated and no claims can be asserted from the contract, because these are barred (Statute of limitations: three years). Data whose further retention is required for evidential purposes shall be exempted from the cancellation until final clarification of the incident.

## 23\. Retrieving profile pictures at Gravatar

23.1. We use the service Gravatar, Automattic, Inc. 132 Hawthorne Street San Francisco, CA 94107, USA, within our website and specifically on the blog.

23.2. Gravatar is a service that allows users to log in and submit profile pictures and their email addresses. If users with the respective e-mail address on other online sites (especially in blogs) leave posts or comments, so their profile pictures can be displayed next to the posts or comments. For this purpose, the e-mail address communicated by the users to Gravatar is transmitted encrypted in order to check whether a profile is stored for it. This is the sole purpose of sending the e-mail address and it will not be used for other purposes, but will be deleted afterwards.

23.3. The use of Gravatar is based on our legitimate interests within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f) GDPR, because with the help of Gravatar we offer the post and comment writers the opportunity to personalize their posts with a profile picture.

23.4. Automattic is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000CbqcAAC&status=Active).](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000CbqcAAC&status=Active\).)

23.5. By displaying the images, Gravatar has learned the IP address of the users, as this is necessary for communication between a browser and an online service. For more information about Gravatar's collection and use of data, see the Automattic Privacy Notice: <https://automattic.com/privacy/>.

23.6. If users do not want a user picture linked to their email address on Gravatar to appear in the comments, they should use a non-Gravatar email address to comment. We also point out that it is also possible to use an anonymous email address if users do not want their own email address to be sent to Gravatar.

Users can completely prevent the transfer of data by not using our commenting system.

## 24\. Akismet anti-spam check

24.1. Our website uses the "Akismet" service offered by Automattic, Inc. 132 Hawthorne Street San Francisco, CA 94107, USA. The use is based on our legitimate interests within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR. With the help of this service, comments of real people are distinguished from spam comments. All comment information is sent to a server in the US, where it is analyzed and stored for four days for comparison. If a comment has been classified as spam, the data will be stored beyond that time. This information includes the name entered, the email address, the IP address, the comment content, the referrer, details of the browser used, the computer system and the time of the entry.

24.2. Automattic is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000CbqcAAC&status=Active).](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000CbqcAAC&status=Active\).)

24.3. For more information about the collection and use of data by Akismet, see the Automattic Privacy Notice: <https://automattic.com/privacy/>.

24.4. Users are welcome to use pseudonyms, or to refrain from entering the name or email address. You can completely prevent the transfer of data by not using our commenting system.

## 25\. Collection of access data and logfiles

25.1. Based on our legitimate interests within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR Data on every access to the server on which this service is located (so-called server log files). The access data includes name of the retrieved web page, file, date and time of retrieval, amount of data transferred, message about successful retrieval, browser type and version, the user's operating system, referrer URL (the previously visited page), IP address and the requesting provider ,

25.2. Logfile information is stored for security purposes (for example, to investigate hacker attacks, abusive or fraudulent activities) for a maximum of 60 days and then deleted. Data whose further retention is required for evidential purposes shall be exempted from the cancellation until final clarification of the incident.

## 26\. Online presence in social media 

26.1. We maintain online presence within social networks and platforms in order to communicate with customers, prospects and users active there and to inform them about our services. When calling the respective networks and platforms, the terms and conditions and the data processing guidelines apply to their respective operators.

26.2. Unless otherwise stated in our Privacy Policy, we process users' data as long as they communicate with us within social networks and platforms, e.g. Write posts on our online presence or send us messages.

## 27\. Google Analytics

27.1. On the basis of our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 (f) GDPR) Google Analytics, a web analytics service of Google LLC ("Google") ) on. Google uses cookies. The information generated by the cookie about the use of the website by the users are usually transmitted to a Google server in the USA and stored there.

27.2. Google is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI&status=Active](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI&status=Active)).

27.3. Google will use this information on our behalf to evaluate the use of our website by users, to compile reports on the activities within this website and to provide us with further services related to the use of this website and the internet usage. In this case, pseudonymous usage profiles of the users can be created from the processed data.

27.4. We use Google Analytics to display advertisements displayed within Google and its affiliate advertising services, only those users who have shown an interest in our website or who have certain characteristics (eg interests in specific topics or products visited by them) Web pages) that we submit to Google (so-called "remarketing" or "Google Analytics audiences"). With Remarketing Audiences, we also want to make sure that our ads are in line with the potential interest of users and are not annoying.

27.5. We only use Google Analytics with activated IP anonymization. This means that the IP address of the users will be shortened by Google within member states of the European Union or in other contracting states of the Agreement on the European Economic Area. Only in exceptional cases will the full IP address be sent to a Google server in the US and shortened there.

27.6. The IP address submitted by the user's browser will not be merged with other data provided by Google. Users can prevent the storage of cookies by setting their browser software accordingly; Users may also prevent the collection by Google of the data generated by the cookie and related to their use of the website as well as the processing of this data by Google by downloading and installing the browser plug-in available under the following link: <https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=en>

27.7. As an alternative to the browser add-on, especially for browsers on mobile devices, you can prevent the collection by Google Analytics by clicking on this link. An opt-out cookie will be set which prevents the future collection of your data when you visit this website. The opt-out cookie is only valid in this browser and only for our website and is stored on your device. If you delete the cookies in this browser, you must set the opt-out cookie again.

27.8. For more information about Google's data usage, hiring and opt-out options, please visit Google's websites: <https://www.google.com/intl/en/policies/privacy/partners> ("Google's use of your data when you use websites or apps Our Partners "), <https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads> (" Advertising Use of Data "), <https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated> (" Managing information Google uses to show you advertising ").

27.9. The data sent by us and linked to cookies, user IDs (eg user ID) or advertising IDs will be automatically deleted after 14 months. The deletion of data whose retention period has been reached is done automatically once a month.

## 28\. Marketing of advertising space via QUARTER MEDIA 

28.1. Based on our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR, we use the services of QUARTER MEDIA GmbH, Hamburger Str. 152, 22083 Hamburg, (hereinafter "QM") for the marketing of our outer advertising spaces.

28.2. As part of the marketing agreement, so-called AdTags will be integrated on the side of the person responsible, through which QM will deliver advertising. Location-related data can be used to record location-based advertising and for statistical purposes. These data are not processed personally. If a location via the IP address, it is ensured that this is previously anonymized by shortening the last eight digits. Cookies are also used by QM to analyze the use of the websites, in particular online advertising, in anonymised or pseudonymised form and to present to the respective user, on the basis of his preferences, special offers of interest to him on the website.

28.3. QM allows other companies (for example, media agencies, DMPs) to put cookies to analyze the use of online advertising and -Content and you special based on your preferences to present interesting advertising on we market online services for you. List of Companies with their privacy policies: (Amazon A9 / Amazon Europe core S.à.rl (<https://www.a9.com/cou/)>,Criteo GmbH (<https://www.criteo.com/privacy/)> Define Media GmbH <http://www.definemedia.de/datenschutz/)>, DoubleClick / Google LLC (<http://www.google.com/policies/technologies/ads)>, Future TV GmbH (https: //www.futuretv-group. com / privacy-policy /), [m] Platform / GroupM Germany GmbH (www.groupm.com/mplatform-privacy-policy)) Index Exchange Inc. (www.indexexchange.com/privacy)) OpenX GmbH (www.openx .com / legal / privacy-policy /) • Spotx GmbH (<https://www.spotx.tv/privacy-policy/)> Tisoomi GmbH (<http://www.tisoomi.com/datasecurity.html)> Yieldlab AG ([www.yieldlab.de/meta-navigation/datenschutz/](http://www.yieldlab.de/meta-navigation/datenschutz/)).

28.4. Further information on the collection and use of the data by QM can be found in QM's privacy policy: <https://quartermedia.de/datenschutzerklaerung/>

28.5. If users do not want cookies stored on their computer, they will be asked to disable the option in their browser's system settings. Saved cookies can be deleted in the system settings of the browser. The exclusion of cookies can lead to functional restrictions of this website.

28.6. If you wish to oppose the interest-based advertising by QM and its partners, you can use the preference manager on this page: <http://meine-cookies.org/cookies_verwalten/praeferenzmanager.html>.

## 29\. Google Re / marketing services

29.1. On the basis of our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 (f) GDPR) we use the marketing and remarketing services ("Google"). Marketing Services ") of Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheater Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA, (" Google ").

29.2. Google is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI&status=Active).](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI&status=Active\).)

29.3. Google Marketing Services allows us to better target advertisements for and on our website so that we only present ads to users that potentially match their interests. If a user e.g. Showing ads for products he's been interested in on other websites is called remarketing. For these purposes, when Google and our other websites accessing Google Marketing Services are directly accessed by Google, a code will be executed by Google and so-called (re) marketing tags (invisible graphics or code, also called "Web Beacons ") incorporated into the website. With their help, the user is provided with an individual cookie, i. a small file is saved (instead of cookies, comparable technologies can also be used). The cookies can be set by different domains, including google.com, doubleclick.net, invitemedia.com, admeld.com, googlesyndication.com or googleadservices.com. In this file is noted which web pages the user visited, for what content he is interested and what offers he has clicked, as well as technical information about the browser and operating system, referring web pages, visit time and other information on the use of the website. The IP address of the users is also recorded, whereby in the context of Google Analytics we announce that the IP address is shortened within member states of the European Union or other parties to the Agreement on the European Economic Area and only in exceptional cases to one Google server in the US is transmitted and shortened there. The IP address will not be merged with data of the user within other offers from Google. The above information may also be linked by Google with such information from other sources. If the user then visits other websites, they can be displayed according to his interests, the ads tailored to him.

29.4. The data of the users are pseudonym processed in the context of the Google marketing services. That Google stores and processes e.g. not the name or e-mail address of the users, but processes the relevant data cookie-related within pseudonymous user profiles. That from the perspective of Google, the ads are not managed and displayed to a specifically identified person, but to the cookie owner, regardless of who that cookie owner is. This does not apply if a user has explicitly allowed Google to process the data without this pseudonymization. The information collected about users through Google Marketing Services is transmitted to Google and stored on Google's servers in the United States.

29.5. Among the Google marketing services we use is u.a. the online advertising program "Google AdWords". In the case of Google AdWords, each advertiser receives a different "conversion cookie". Cookies can not be tracked through AdWords advertisers' websites. The information collected through the cookie is used to generate conversion statistics for AdWords advertisers who have opted for conversion tracking. Advertisers will see the total number of users who clicked on their ad and were redirected to a conversion tracking tag page. However, they do not receive information that personally identifies users.

29.6. We can engage third-party ads based on Google's DoubleClick marketing service. DoubleClick uses cookies that enable Google and its affiliate websites to serve ads based on users' visits to this site or other sites on the Internet.

29.7. We use the "AdSense" service, which displays advertisements on our website and wages us for their display or other use. For these purposes, usage data, e.g. the click on an ad and the IP address of the users processed, whereby the IP address is shortened by the last two places. Therefore, the processing of the users' data is pseudonymised. We use Adsense with non-personalized ads. The ads are not displayed based on user profiles. Non-personalized ads are not based on past user behavior. Targeting uses contextual information, including coarse (eg, on-site) geotargeting based on the current location, content on the current website or app, and current search terms. Google prohibits any personalized targeting, including demographic targeting and user list targeting.

29.8. Also we can use the service "Google Optimizer". Google Optimizer allows us to understand how various changes to a website (such as changes to the input fields, the design, etc.) can take place in so-called "A / B testings". Cookies are stored on users' devices for these purposes. Only pseudonymous data of the users are processed.

29.9. In addition, we may use the "Google Tag Manager" to integrate and manage the Google Analytics and Marketing Services on our website.

29.10. For more information about Google's data usage for marketing purposes, please visit the overview page: <https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads>, Google's Privacy Policy is available at <https://policies.google.com/privacy>.

29.11. If you wish to opt-out of interest-based advertising through Google Marketing Services, you can take advantage of Google's recruitment and opt-out options: <https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated.> Any personalized targeting, including demographic targeting and user list targeting.

## 30\. Facebook

30.1. On the basis of our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. (fg. GDPR)) we use the social network facebook.com, which is operated by Facebook Ireland Ltd., 4 Grand Canal Square, Grand Canal Harbor, Dublin 2, Ireland ("Facebook").

30.2. Facebook is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000GnywAAC&status=Active](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000GnywAAC&status=Active)).

30.3. When a user clicks on a Facebook button on our website and he is logged in to his Facebook account, his device establishes a direct connection to the Facebook servers. In the process, user profiles can be created from the processed data. We therefore have no influence on the amount of data that Facebook collects as a result of the click and therefore inform the users according to our level of knowledge.

30.4. By clicking Facebook receives the information that a user has accessed the corresponding page of the website. If the user is logged in to Facebook, Facebook can assign the visit to his Facebook account. For example, if users press the Facebook Like button or leave a comment, the information is sent from your device directly to Facebook and stored there. If a user is not a member of Facebook, there is still the possibility that Facebook will find out and save their IP address. According to Facebook, only an anonymous IP address is stored in Germany.

30.5. The purpose and scope of the data collection and the further processing and use of the data by Facebook, as well as the related rights and setting options for protecting the privacy of users, can be found in Facebook's privacy policy: <https://www.facebook.com/about/privacy/>.

30.6. If a user is a Facebook member and does not want Facebook to collect data about him via this website and link it to his member data stored on Facebook, he must log out of Facebook and delete his cookies before using our website. Other settings and inconsistencies regarding the use of data for advertising purposes are possible within the Facebook profile settings: <https://www.facebook.com/settings?tab=ads> or via the US-American site [http://www.aboutads.info](http://www.aboutads.info/) / choices / or the EU page [http://www.youronlinechoices.com/.](http://www.youronlinechoices.com/) The settings are platform independent, i. they are adopted for all devices, such as desktop computers or mobile devices.

## 31\. Bing Ads

31.1. Based on our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) lit. GDPR), we base our website on the conversion and tracking tool "Bing Ads" Microsoft Corporation, One Microsoft Way, Redmond, WA 98052-6399, USA. Microsoft stores cookies on the users' devices in order to allow users to analyze the use of our website as long as users have accessed our website via a Microsoft Bing ad (so-called "conversion measurement"). Microsoft and we can thus recognize that someone clicked on an ad, was redirected to our website, and reached a previously determined landing page (called the "conversion page"). We only hear the total number of users who clicked on a Bing ad and were then redirected to the conversion page. No IP addresses are stored. No personal information on the identity of the users is given.

31.2. Microsoft is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000KzNaAAK&status=Active](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000KzNaAAK&status=Active)).

31.3. If users do not want to participate in the Bing Ads tracking process, you may opt out of setting a cookie by browser setting or using the Microsoft opt-out page: <http://choice.microsoft.com/> -DE / opt-out.

31.4. For more information about privacy and cookies on Microsoft Bing Ads, please refer to the Microsoft Privacy Policy: <https://privacy.microsoft.com/en-us/privacystatement>.

## 32\. VG Wort / Scalable Central Measurement Method

32.1. We use the "Scalable Central Measurement Method" (SZM) of INFOnline GmbH (INFOnline GmbH, Brühler Str. 9, D-53119 Bonn.) For the determination of statistical parameters for determining the copy probability of texts. Anonymous measurements are taken. Alternatively, traffic metering uses a session cookie or signature created from various automatically transmitted information from your browser to recognize computer systems. IP addresses are only processed in anonymous form. The procedure was developed in compliance with data protection. The only goal of the procedure is to determine the copy probability of individual texts. At no time individual users are identified. Your identity always remains protected. You will not receive advertising through the system.

32.2. Many of our pages are provided with JavaScript calls, through which we report the access to the collecting society Wort (VG Wort). We allow our authors to participate in the distributions of the VG Wort, which complies with the legal remuneration for the use of copyrighted works in accordance with Art. § 53 UrhG. 32.3. Usage data and metadata of the users are processed here, the IP addresses being shortened and the measuring methods being pseudonymous. The shortened IP address is stored for a maximum of 60 days. The usage data in connection with a pseudonymous assignment value ("Identifier") are stored for a maximum of 6 months. 32.4. Users are also provided with an opt-out in order to disagree with the collection for the aforementioned purposes: [https://optout.ioam.de](https://optout.ioam.de/). Further information can be found in the data protection statement of INFOnline here: <https://www.infonline.de/datenschutz/benutzer>.

## 33\. Jetpack (WordPress Stats)

33.1. Based on our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 (f) GDPR) we use the plugin Jetpack (here the subfunction "Wordpress Stats") , which integrates a visitor access statistics evaluation tool, and Automattic, Inc. 132 Hawthorne Street San Francisco, CA 94107, USA. Jetpack uses so-called "cookies", text files that are stored on your computer and that allow an analysis of the use of the website by you.

33.2. Automattic is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000CbqcAAC&status=Active).](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000CbqcAAC&status=Active\).) 33.3. The information generated by the cookie about your use of this website is stored on a server in the USA. Here, user profiles of the users can be created from the processed data, these being used only for analysis and not for advertising purposes. For more information, see the Automattic Privacy Policy: <https://automattic.com/privacy/> and Jetpack Cookies: <https://jetpack.com/support/cookies/>.

## 34\. Criteo

34.1. Based on our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Article 6 (1) sentence 1 (f) GDPR), we use the services of the provider Criteo GmbH, Gewürzmühlstr. 11, 80538 Munich, Germany.

34.2. Criteo's services allow us to better target advertisements for and on our website so that we only present users with ads that are potentially in their interests. If a user e.g. Showing ads for products he's been interested in on other websites is called remarketing. For this purpose, when Criteo calls our and other websites on which Criteo is active, Criteo immediately executes a Criteo code and so-called (re) marketing tags (invisible graphics or code, also known as web beacons "designated"). With their help, the user is provided with an individual cookie, i. a small file is saved (instead of cookies, comparable technologies can also be used). In this file is noted which web pages the user visited, for what content he is interested and what offers he has clicked, as well as technical information about the browser and operating system, referring web pages, visit time and other information on the use of the website. The above information may also be shared by Criteo with such information from other sources. If the user then visits other websites, they can be displayed according to his interests, the ads tailored to him. 34.3. For more information, as well as how to opt out of Criteo, see the Criteo Privacy Policy: <http://www.criteo.com/privacy/>

## 35\. Tisoomi

35.1. Based on our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR iVm. Art. 28 GDPR) for the advertisement of advertising tisoomi-services (tisoomi GmbH, Gänsemarkt 31, 20354 Hamburg). tisoomi uses so-called "cookies", text files that are stored on your computer and that allow an interest-based display of advertising. The information generated by the cookie about your use of this website (including your IP address) is transmitted to a server of tisoomi in Germany and stored there pseudonymized. tisoomi will use this information to optimize the content of advertising material and, if necessary, to compile reports for the website operators. You can prevent the installation of cookies by setting your browser software accordingly. By using this website, you agree to the processing of the data collected by tisoomi and the manner of processing described above for the stated purpose.

35.2. You can object to the interest-based advertising of tisoomi at any time by using the opt-out option on the following page: <https://www.tisoomi-services.com/datasecurity>.

## 36\. Plista

36.1. Based on our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 (f) GDPR) we use a fully automatic recommendation technology from plista GmbH, Torstrasse 33 , 10119 Berlin.

36.2. With the help of this technology, we want to improve the usability of our website by recommending to you, our visitors, articles and adverts that are tailored to your individual interests (so-called usage-based advertising). In order to be able to exploit usage-based advertising, plista uses cookies on all the websites of the plista partner network to collect information about the usage behavior of website visitors (so-called usage data) and combines these with a random identifier (so-called Cookie ID) assigned by plista to create pseudonymous user profiles. More information on this and the privacy of plista can be found at [https://www.plista.com/en/about/privacy/.](https://www.plista.com/en/about/privacy/)

36.3. Of course, you are always free to deactivate plista's usage-based advertising by declaring your opt-out at [https://www.plista.com/en/about/opt-out/.](https://www.plista.com/en/about/opt-out/)

## 37\. Amazon Affiliate Program

37.1. The person in charge is a participant in the Affiliate Program of Amazon Europe S.à. r. l. and Affiliate to the Advertising Program designed to provide a medium for websites that earn advertising reimbursements through the placement of advertisements and links to amazon.co.uk. We are interested in the program to show you advertisements of interest to you and make our site more interesting to our users.

37.2. The provision of the advertisements collects statistical information about you that is processed by our advertising partners. By visiting the website, Amazon receives the information that you have accessed the corresponding page of our website. Amazon uses web beacons to determine your needs and, if necessary, sets a cookie on your computer. The data mentioned in § 3 of this declaration will be transmitted. We have no influence on the collected data, nor are we aware of the full extent of the data collection and the duration of storage. If you are logged in to Amazon, your data can be assigned directly to your local account. If you do not want to be associated with your Amazon profile, you must log out. It is possible that your data will be shared with Amazon and government contractors.

We have no influence on the collected data, nor are we aware of the full extent of the data collection. The data is transmitted to the USA and evaluated there. The legal basis for the processing of your data is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR.

37.3. You can prevent the installation of the cookies of the Amazon affiliate program in various ways: a) by a corresponding setting of your browser software, in particular the suppression of third party cookies leads to the fact that you do not receive advertisements from third-party providers; b) by deactivating interest-based ads on Amazon via the link <http://www.amazon.de/gp/dra/info>; c) by deactivating the interest-based advertisements of the providers that are part of the "About Ads" self-regulation campaign via the link <http://www.aboutads.info/choices>, these settings being deleted when you delete your cookies. We point out that in this case you may not be able to use all features of this offer in full.

37.4. Further information on the purpose and scope of the data collection and its processing, as well as further information on your rights and setting options for the protection of your privacy can be found in the above-mentioned Privacy Policy: Amazon EU S.à.rl, Amazon Services Europe S.à .r. l. and the Amazon Media EU S.à.r. l., all three resident 5, Rue Plaetis, L-2338 Luxembourg; E-Mail: ad-feedback@amazon.de. Amazon has submitted to the EU-US Privacy Shield, <https://www.privacyshield.gov/EU-US> Framework. For more information about Amazon's data usage, please read the company's privacy policy: <http://www.amazon.com/gp/help/customer/display.html/ref>=footer_privacy?ie=UTF8&nodeId=3312401 and visit: http: // [www.amazon.de/gp/BIT/InternetBasedAds](http://www.amazon.de/gp/BIT/InternetBasedAds).

## 38\. Newsletter

38.1. With the following information we inform you about the contents of our newsletter as well as the registration, dispatch and statistical evaluation procedures as well as your right of objection. By subscribing to our newsletter, you agree to the receipt and the procedures described.

38.2. Content of the newsletter: We send newsletters, e-mails and other electronic notifications with advertising information (hereinafter "newsletter") only with the consent of the recipient or a legal permission. Insofar as the contents of a newsletter are concretely described, they are authoritative for the consent of the users. Incidentally, our newsletters contain information about our products, offers, promotions and our company.

38.3. Double opt-in and logging: Registration for our newsletter is done in a so-called double-opt-in procedure. That After registration, you will receive an e-mail asking you to confirm your registration. This confirmation is necessary so that nobody can register with external e-mail addresses. The registration for the newsletter will be logged in order to prove the registration process according to the legal requirements. This includes the storage of the login and the confirmation time, as well as the IP address. Likewise, changes to your data stored with the shipping service provider will be logged.

38.4. Shipping service provider for JuraForum.de: The newsletter is sent by rapidmail GmbH, Augustinerplatz 2, 79098 Freiburg i.Br., Germany. The privacy policy of this shipping service provider can be viewed here: <https://www.rapidmail.de/datenschutzbestimmungen/>

38.5. Shipping service for connektar.de and Gartenbista.de: GetResponse Sp. Z o.o. with registered office in Gdansk, Poland, ul. Arkonska 6, A3, 80-387 Gdansk. The privacy policy of the shipping service provider can be viewed here: <https://www.getresponse.de/email-marketing/legal/datenschutz.html.> In the following both referred to as "shipping service provider".

38.6. Furthermore, the shipping service provider may, according to its own information, transmit these data in pseudonymous form, i. without assignment to a user, to optimize or improve their own services, e.g. for the technical optimization of the dispatch and the presentation of the newsletters or for statistical purposes, to determine from which countries the recipients come. However, the shipping service provider does not use the data of our newsletter recipients to write them down or to pass them on to third parties.

38.7. Credentials: To subscribe to the newsletter, it is sufficient to provide your e-mail address. Optionally, we ask you to give a name in the newsletter for personal address.

38.8. Measuring success: The newsletters contain a so-called "web beacon", i. a pixel-sized file that is retrieved from the shipping service provider's server when the newsletter is opened. This call will initially collect technical information, such as information about the browser and your system, as well as your IP address and time of retrieval. This information is used to improve the technical performance of services based on their specifications or audience and their reading habits, based on their locations (which can be determined using the IP address) or access times. Statistical surveys also include determining if the newsletters will be opened, when they will be opened and which links will be clicked. For technical reasons, this information can be assigned to the individual newsletter recipients. However, it is neither our endeavor nor that of the shipping service provider to observe individual users. The evaluations serve us much more to recognize the reading habits of our users and to adapt our content to them or to send different content according to the interests of our users.

38.9. The dispatch of the newsletter and the success measurement are made on the basis of a consent of the recipients acc. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a), Art. 7 GDPR in connection with § 7 Abs. 2 Nr. 3 UWG or on the basis of the legal permission according to Art. § 7 Abs. 3 UWG. 38.10. When registering for our Garden Bista Newsletter, your declaration of consent pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows: "By clicking on" Request now "you agree to receive the newsletter of Gartenbista.de for the purpose of information and advertising for offers on the topics of home and garden and our company .. Consent, reader analysis, shipping service and right of withdrawal according to. Data protection."

38.11. When signing up for our connektar newsletter, your declaration of consent pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows: "Yes, I agree to receive the connektar newsletter for the purpose of informing and promoting PR, online marketing and press services as well as our company. You can revoke this consent at any time, e.g. via unsubscribe link at the end of the newsletter. Information on data protection, shipping service providers, performance measurement and logging can be found in our privacy policy. "

38.12. When registering for our openPR newsletter, your declaration of consent pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows: "Yes, I have read the privacy policy (link) and I agree, in particular I agree to receive the press newsletter from openPR for the purpose of information and promotion for offers on the subject PR, online Marketing and press as well as our company. You can revoke this consent at any time, e.g. via unsubscribe link at the end of the newsletter.

38.13. When registering for our JuraForum newsletter, your declaration of consent pursuant to Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a) GDPR as follows: By clicking on "Registration" you agree to receive the JuraForum newsletter for the purpose of information and promotion for offers on the subjects of law, legal advice and finance / taxes as well as our company. You can revoke this consent at any time, e.g. via unsubscribe link at the end of the newsletter. Consent, reader analysis, shipping service and right of withdrawal are in accordance with. Data protection.

38.14. The logging of the registration process is based on our legitimate interests in accordance with. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR and serves as proof of consent to the receipt of the newsletter.

38.15. Termination / Revocation: You can terminate the receipt of our newsletter at any time, i. Revoke your consent. A link to cancel the newsletter can be found at the end of each newsletter. If the users have only subscribed to the newsletter and terminated this registration, their personal data will be deleted.

## 39\. Web hosting

39.1. We use external providers for webhosting (webhosting). For the purpose of secure and uninterrupted operation of our online services, external providers provide web servers and database servers.

39.2. The web hosts process stock data, contract data, payment data, meta and communication data of customers, prospects and users of the websites. The legal basis of the processing is Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. f) GDPR i.V.m. Art. 28 GDPR. We have concluded order processing agreements. Our legitimate interest lies in the secure, uninterrupted and efficient operation of our online services.

## 40\. Integration of services and content of third parties 

40.1. Based on our legitimate interests (ie interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our website within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) sentence 1 f) of the GDPR), we make use of third-party content or service offerings within our website their contents and services, such as Include videos or fonts (collectively referred to as "content"). This always presupposes that the third-party providers of this content perceive the IP address of the users, since they could not send the content to their browser without the IP address. The IP address is therefore required for the presentation of this content. We endeavor to use only content whose respective providers use the IP address solely for the delivery of the content. Third parties may also use so-called pixel tags (invisible graphics, also referred to as "web beacons") for statistical or marketing purposes. The "pixel tags" can be used to evaluate information such as visitor traffic on the pages of this website. The pseudonymous information may also be stored in cookies on the user's device and may include, but is not limited to, technical information about the browser and operating system, referring web sites, visit time, and other information regarding the use of our website.

40.2. The following presentation provides an overview of third-party providers as well as their contents, as well as links to their data protection statements, which contain further information on the processing of data and, for already mentioned here, contradictory possibilities (so-called opt-out) contain:

**Google Fonts**

External fonts from Google, LLC., [Https://www.google.com/fonts](https://www.google.com/fonts) ("Google Fonts"). The integration of Google fonts is done by a server call on Google (usually in the US). Privacy Policy: <https://policies.google.com/privacy>, opt-out: <https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated.>

**Google Maps**

Maps provided by the third-party Google Maps service, Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheater Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA. Privacy Policy: <https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/>, opt-out: <https://www.google.com/settings/ads/>.

**YouTube**

Third-party platform "YouTube" videos Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheater Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA. Privacy Policy: <https://policies.google.com/privacy>, opt-out: <https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated>.

**Google ReCaptcha       **

We bind the function to detect bots, e.g. when entering into online forms ("ReCaptcha") of the provider Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheater Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA. Privacy Policy: <https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/>, opt-out: <https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated>.

**Google+**

Within our website links to the service Google+ are included. Google+ is powered by Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheater Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, United States. If you are logged in to your Google+ account, you can link or rate the content of our pages to your Google+ profile by clicking the Google+ button. This allows Google to associate your visit to our pages with your user account. We point out that we as the provider of the pages are not aware of the content of the transmitted data and their use by Google+. Privacy Policy: <https://policies.google.com/privacy>, opt-out: <https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated>.

**Instagram**

Within our website, links to the Instagram service are included. Instagram is offered by: Instagram Inc., 1601 Willow Road, Menlo Park, CA, 94025, United States. If you are logged in to your Instagram account, you can link or share the contents of our pages with your Instagram profile by clicking on the Instagram button. This allows Instagram to associate the visit to our pages with your user account. We point out that we as the provider of the pages do not receive knowledge of the content of the transmitted data and their use by Instagram. Privacy Policy: <http://instagram.com/about/legal/privacy/>.

**Linkedin**

Within our websiteing we use links to the LinkedIn network (LinkedIn Corporation, 2029 Stierlin Court, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA). If you are logged in to your Linkedin account, you can share the contents of our pages in your Linkedin account by clicking on the Linkedin button. LinkedIn is informed that you have visited our website with your IP address. If you are registered with LinkedIn, LinkedIn will be able to associate your interaction with our websiteing with your user account. LinkedIn is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000L0UZAA0&status=Active).](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000L0UZAA0&status=Active\).) Privacy Policy: <https://www.linkedin.com/legal/privacy-policy>, opt-out: <https://www.linkedin.com/psettings/guest-controls/retargeting-opt-out>.

**Pinterest**

We use links to the Pinterest social network operated by Pinterest Inc., 635 High Street, Palo Alto, CA, 94301, USA ("Pinterest"). If you are logged in to your Pinterest account, you can link or share the contents of our pages with your Pinterest profile by clicking on the Pinterest button. If so, your browser connects directly to the Pinterest servers. Log data is transmitted to the Pinterest server in the USA. This log data may include your IP address, the address of the websites visited, which also includes Pinterest features, browser type and settings, the date and time of the request, how you use Pinterest, and cookies. Privacy Policy: <https://about.pinterest.com/en/privacy-policy>.

**Twitter**

Within our website, we have included links to the service Twitter (hereinafter referred to as "Twitter"). Twitter is an offer from Twitter Inc., 1355 Market Street, Suite 900, San Francisco, CA 94103, United States. If you are logged in to your Twitter account, you can link or share the contents of our pages with your Twitter profile by clicking on the Twitter button. We use the following Twitter functions: Presentation of our contributions within Twitter within our local website, the link to our profile on Twitter and the opportunity to interact with the posts and features of Twitter. Twitter is certified under the Privacy Shield Agreement, which provides a guarantee to comply with European privacy legislation ([https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000TORzAAO&status=Active).](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000TORzAAO&status=Active\).) Privacy Policy: <https://twitter.com/privacy>, Opt-Out: <https://twitter.com/personalization>.

**XING**

We use links to the network XING. Provider is the XING AG, Dammtorstraße 29-32, 20354 Hamburg, Germany. Each time you click on the Xing button on one of our pages, you will be connected to Xing servers when you are logged in to your XING account. A storage of personal data is not done to our knowledge. In particular, no IP addresses are stored or the usage behavior is evaluated. Privacy Policy: <https://www.xing.com/app/share?op=data_protection.>

**jQuery**

External code of the JavaScript framework "jQuery" provided by the third-party jQuery Foundation, [https://jquery.org](https://jquery.org/).

## 41\. Data protection in applications and in the application process

41.1. Applications sent electronically or by post to the person in charge will be processed electronically or manually for the purposes of processing the application process.

41.2. We expressly point out that application documents with "special categories of personal data" according to Art. 9 GDPR (eg a photo, which gives an indication of your ethnic origin, religion or marital status), with the exception of any severe disability, which you choose want to disclose, are undesirable. You should submit your application without this data. This does not affect your candidate chances.

41.3. The legal basis for processing is Art. 6 para. 1 p. 1 lit. b) GDPR and § 26 BDSG n.F ..

41.4. If, after the completion of the application process, an employment relationship with the applicant is received, the applicant data will be stored in compliance with relevant data protection legislation. If no job is offered to you after completing the application process, your application letter and documents will be deleted 6 months after the cancellation has been sent, in order to be able to satisfy any claims and proof obligations according to AGG.

## 42\. Right of information

If you process personal data, you are i.S.d. GDPR and you have the following rights to the person responsible:

42.1. **Right of information**

You may ask the person in charge to confirm if personal data concerning you is processed by us. If such processing is available, you can request information from the person responsible about the following information:

  * the purposes for which the personal data are processed;
  * the categories of personal data that are processed;
  * the recipients or the categories of recipients to whom the personal data relating to you have been disclosed or are still being disclosed;
  * the planned duration of storage of your personal data or, if specific information is not available, criteria for determining the duration of storage;
  * the right of rectification or erasure of personal data concerning you, a right to restriction of processing by the controller or a right to object to such processing;
  * the existence of a right of appeal to a supervisory authority;
  * all available information on the source of the data if the personal data are not collected from the data subject;
  * the existence of automated decision-making including profiling under Article 22 (1) and (4) GDPR and - at least in these cases - meaningful information about the logic involved, and the scope and intended impact of such processing on the data subject.
  * You have the right to request information about whether your personal information relates to a third country or an international organization. In this connection, you can request the appropriate guarantees in accordance with. Art. 46 GDPR in connection with the transfer.

42.2. **Right to rectification**

You have a right to rectification and / or completion to the controller, if the personal data you process is incorrect or incomplete. The responsible person must make the correction without delay.

42.3. **Right to restriction of processing**

You may request the restriction of the processing of your personal data:

  * if you deny the accuracy of your personal information for a period of time that enables the controller to verify the accuracy of your personal information;
  * the processing is unlawful and you refuse to delete the personal data and instead request the restriction of the use of personal data;
  * the controller no longer needs personal information for the purposes of processing, but you need it to assert, exercise or defend legal claims; or
  * if you have objected to the processing pursuant to Art. 21 (1) GDPR and it is not yet certain whether the legitimate reasons of the person responsible prevail over your reasons.

If the processing of personal data concerning you has been restricted, this data may only be used with your consent or for the purpose of asserting, exercising or defending legal claims or protecting the rights of another natural or legal person or for reasons of important public interest Union or a Member State. If the limitation of the processing after the o.g. If conditions are restricted, you will be informed by the person in charge before the restriction is lifted.

42.4. **Right to delete**

42.4.1. You may require the controller to delete your personal information without delay, and the controller is required to delete that information immediately if one of the following is true:

  * The personal data concerning you are no longer necessary for the purposes for which they were collected or otherwise processed.
  * You revoke your consent to the processing in accordance with. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a) or Art. 9 para. 2 lit. (a) GDPR and there is no other legal basis for the processing.
  * You place gem. Art. 21 para. 1 GDPR objection to the processing and there are no prior justifiable reasons for the processing, or you lay gem. Art. 21 para. 2 GDPR Opposition to processing.
  * Your personal data has been processed unlawfully.
  * The deletion of personal data concerning you is required to fulfill a legal obligation under Union or national law to which the controller is subject.
  * The personal data concerning you were collected in relation to information society services offered pursuant to Art. 8 (1) GDPR.

42.4.2. If the person in charge has made the personal data concerning you public and is acc. Article 17 (1) of the GDPR, it shall take appropriate measures, including technical means, to inform data controllers who process the personal data that you have been identified as being affected, taking into account available technology and implementation costs Persons requesting deletion of all links to such personal data or of copies or replications of such personal data.

42.4.3. The right to erasure does not exist if the processing is necessary

  * to exercise the right to freedom of expression and information;
  * to fulfill a legal obligation which requires processing under the law of the Union or of the Member States to which the controller is subject or for the performance of a task of public interest or in the exercise of official authority delegated to the controller;
  * for reasons of public interest in the field of public health pursuant to Art. 9 (2) lit. h and i and Art. 9 (3) GDPR;
  * for archival purposes of public interest, scientific or historical research purposes or for statistical purposes acc. Article 89 (1) GDPR, to the extent that the law referred to in subparagraph (a) is likely to render impossible or seriously affect the achievement of the objectives of that processing, or
  * to assert, exercise or defend legal claims.

42.5. **Right of informing**

If you have the right of rectification, erasure or restriction of processing to the controller, he / she is obliged to notify all recipients to whom your personal data have been disclosed of this correction or deletion of the data or restriction of processing, unless: this proves to be impossible or involves a disproportionate effort. You have a right to the person responsible to be informed about these recipients

42.6. **Right to data portability**

You have the right to receive personally identifiable information you provide to the controller in a structured, common and machine-readable format. In addition, you have the right to transfer this data to another person without hindrance by the person responsible for providing the personal data, provided that

  * the processing on a consent acc. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. a) GDPR or Art. 9 para. 2 lit. a GDPR or on a contract acc. Art. 6 para. 1 sentence 1 lit. b) GDPR is based and
  * the processing is done using automated procedures.

In exercising this right, you also have the right to obtain that your personal data relating to you are transmitted directly from one person to another, insofar as this is technically feasible. Freedoms and rights of other persons may not be affected. The right to data portability does not apply to the processing of personal data necessary for the performance of a task in the public interest or in the exercise of official authority delegated to the controller.

42.7. Right to object or revoke the processing of your data

If you consent to the processing of your data (Article 6 (1) sentence 1 (a)) or Article 9 (2) lit. a) GDPR), you can revoke them at any time in accordance with Art. 7 (3) GDPR. Such revocation will affect the admissibility of the processing of your personal data after you have given it to us.

Insofar as we base the processing of your personal data on balancing of interests (Article 6 (1) sentence 1 (f) GDPR), you can object to the processing. This is the case if, in particular, the processing is not required to fulfill a contract with you, which we describe in each case in the following description of the functions. In the event of such a disagreement, we ask you to explain the reasons why we should not process your personal data as we have done. In the case of your justified objection, we will examine the situation and will either discontinue or adapt the data processing or point out to you our compelling legitimate reasons on which we continue the processing.

Of course, you may object to the processing of your personal data for advertising and data analysis purposes at any time. About your advertising contradiction you can inform us under the above contact details.

42.8. **Right to complain to a supervisory authority**

Without prejudice to any other administrative or judicial remedy, you shall have the right to complain to a supervisory authority, in particular in the Member State of its residence, place of work or place of alleged infringement, if you believe that the processing of the personal data concerning you is against the GDPR violates. The supervisory authority to which the complaint has been submitted shall inform the complainant of the status and results of the complaint, including the possibility of a judicial remedy pursuant to Article 78 of the GDPR.

## 43\. Security measures

43.1. We take appropriate technical measures in accordance with Art. 32 GDPR, taking into account the state of the art, the implementation costs and the nature, scope, circumstances and purposes of the processing as well as the different likelihood and severity of the risk to the rights and freedoms of natural persons and organizational measures to ensure a level of protection appropriate to the risk; Measures include, in particular, ensuring the confidentiality, integrity and availability of data by controlling physical access to the data, as well as their access, input, disclosure, availability and separation. In addition, we have established procedures that ensure the enjoyment of data subject rights, data erasure and data vulnerability. Furthermore, we consider the protection of personal data already in the development, or selection of hardware, software and procedures, according to the principle of data protection by technology design and by privacy-friendly default settings taken into account (Article 25 GDPR).

43.2. One of the security measures is the encrypted transfer of data between your browser and our server.

## 44\. Changes and updates to the privacy policy

We ask you to inform yourself regularly about the content of our privacy policy. We will adjust the privacy policy as soon as the changes to the data processing we make require it. We will notify you as soon as the changes require your participation (eg consent) or other individual notification.

May, 25th 2018

Privacy statements of the Einbock GmbH valid until 24 May 2018
